ASIF MUNIR



Solutions Architect / Business Systems Analyst Digital & Agile

Address: 48, Pennington Terrace, Bradford, BD5 OPN

Email: azifmunir@hotmail.comMobile #:00447814419513Nationality: BritishDriving License: Full

PROFILE SUMMARY

An accomplished IT consultant with over 11 years of industry experience mainly working in an agile environment and specialising in architecture, business analysis, business transformation, product design and development, change management, and improving customer journeys through bespoke and cloud-based solutions.

Throughout my IT career, I have worked on a number of big and small scale projects to gather the requirements, refining those requirements, writing user stories and proposing a solution. I possess good understanding of all stages of PDLC which helps me understand and refine client's requirements and business needs.

My core skill set includes but not limited to, pre-sales analysis of requirements, proposing a solution, deciding the technologies and infrastructure, stakeholder management, requirement elicitation and documentation using software engineering principles and business analysis techniques, breaking the requirements into features and user stories, defining and writing acceptance criteria, release planning, sprint management and retrospective, organizing refinement sessions and tracking the progress.

KEY SKILLS	
PERSONAL SKILLS	Communication Adaptable Influencing Team work Problem solving

BA/SA SKILLS	Requirements Elicitation, Workshops Facilitation, 1-2-1, Business Process Modelling, Data Analysis, System Analysis, Gap Analysis, ,UAT Support, Stake holder Mgt.
BA/SA DOCUMENTATION	Scoping document, Functional Specs, User Stories & Acceptance Criteria, Process Flows, Use Cases, Wireframes, MoSCoW, RAID
BA/SA TOOLS	JIRA, Confluence, Rally, MS Visio, Balsamiq, UML (Activity, Sequence, State, Use Cases diagrams)
DEV METHODOLOGIES	Agile /Scrum(Sprints, Stand-ups, Planning, Retrospective/Refinement Sessions, User Stories & Acceptance Criteria, TFS, Version 1), Waterfall
DATA ANALYSIS & REPORTING	ETL, SQL, Crystal Reports, DWH (Data Warehousing – Facts/Dimensions), SSRS
DATABASES	SQL, Microsoft SQL Server, MS Access, SSIS
APPLICATIONS	(Digital Services Framework) AZURE, AWS , Web Applications, Windows Applications
DEVELOPMENT SKILLS	Windows & Web Applications, Microsoft VB.NET, ASP.NET GUI Design, Unit Testing, VB6, HTML, Ajax, Java Script, DEVEXPRESS Components, XML, C#. Net, SQL, RESTful API, OAPI, JSON, C/C++ Programming, HTML5, XML python, php, ColdFusion, CSS3, SOAP, Flex, MVC, ETL, NAnt Scripts, VB.Net, Fortron, Java
Concepts and Practices	Agile, Scrum, Waterfall, TOGAF, Object Oriented Programming (OOP), Networking (LAN/Wireless LAN), UML Modeling, Software Lifecycle Methodologies (SDLC), RDB (Relational Database), Software Project Management, OS Installations, MVC, WCF, SOA, SaaS, Cloud Azure, Cloud AWS

PROFESSIONAL QUALIFICATIONS & EDUCATION

QA Training Course for SQL Server 2008
QA Training Course for Scrum Practitioner
TOGAF 9.1 Certified Enterprise Architect
Present with impact

(QA course: https://www.qa.com/training-courses/business-skills/communication/present-with-impact)

M.Sc. Software Engineering (2007-2008) 1st Class Distinction - Bradford University, United Kingdom

BS Honors. Computer Science (2001-2005) 1st Class Distinction - Govt. College University Lahore, Pakistan

WORK EXPERIENCE

SOLUTIONS ARCHITECT / LEAD BUSINESS SYSTEMS ANALYST

BTL GROUP LTD (<u>www.btl.com</u>) Bradford, West Yorkshire, UK Aug 2013 – June 2019

At BTL, I have worked with a wide range of **UK and US based clients** including **City and Guilds**, **British Council**, **AAT**, **AQA**, **RCPCH**, **ICAEW**, **SAXION University**, **SQA**, **EAL**, **WJEC**, **NBME**, **Prometric**. My role entailed understanding customer needs, requirements elicitation and documentation, Business Process analysis, define the MVP and propose an appropriate solution. Guiding development teams throughout the sprint and performing retrospectives. Delivered multiple projects while being involved right from the Project Initiation and seeing through all project phases down to Project Delivery.

RESPONSIBILITIES:

- Involved from the Discovery stage to Implementation stage in PDLC using Agile methodology
- Proposing an appropriate solution based on the business analysis and deciding the appropriate infrastructure (Azure or Private). Also, providing cost model
- Supporting the sales team during the pre-sales phase, working on the requirement sections of RFPs and RFIs and proposing a solution as part of RFP or RFI
- Carry out Data Analysis and Data mapping activities and streamline the ETL pipelines for the DWH projects
- Facilitate workshops and 1-2-1 with Stake Holders and SMEs to understand and establish the pain points
- Map the 'As-Is' and 'To-Be' business processes using UML (in MS Visio) to assist the requirements phase
- Work with the business teams to elicit and analyse business requirements
- Identify the potential Work-Streams and break them down into Epics
- Prepare the Scoping Document/ SOW listing all the high level requirements and get the Stake Holders Sign-off
- Work with the Clients to identify the MVP and later phases using MoSCoW and then further prioritize the requirements in each phase
- Work with the Technical Architect to identify the **Solution Design** and **IT Deliverables** based on the **Scoping Document**
- Create and manage Backlog in Version 1 and documenting User Stories and Acceptance Criteria
- Create screen Prototypes and Wireframes using Balsamiq
- Facilitate **refinement sessions** with the Delivery Team and present the business requirements to **get estimations** for each IT Deliverable
- Work closely with the Developers ensuring the smooth implementation of the project/change without any misinterpretation of requirements

- Work closely with the Testing team ensuring the testing is in-line with the requirements and provide BA signoff of each backlog item before moved into UAT
- Fully involved in **UAT** and **Release Cycles** till **Go-Live**
- Consistently bridge between business and IT ensuring any decisions/queries get clarified from both sides
- Participate in the daily stand-up, planning, refinements, and retrospectives session
- Facilitate regular 'Show & Tell' sessions to the business users and Senior Management

CLIENTS:

British Council, National Board of Medical Examiners United States, Prometric, AAT, SQA, AQA, NEBOSH, CILEX, Trinity College, United Nations, Edutech, Axelos, BRC, IELTS, OUP, ERC, CIEH, ASPEQ, Kaplan, Robert Gordon University, University of St Andrews, and CIEH.

ARTEFACTS:

Scoping Document, Backlog, US & AC, Process Maps, Wireframes, Decision Log, Data Mapping Documents, Data Reports, DFD

TOOLS:

Rally, MS Visio, MS Excel

PROJECTS: (worked on many other projects but just listing some of the significant ones)

Title: NBME LionsGate Project

Client: National Board of Medical Examiners

Year: April 2016-June 2019

Summary:

- Involved from pre-sales stage, working on technical requirements and proposing an overall solution
- Working on SoW for each release and creating features, user stories, providing cost and time estimates
- Making regular trips (2 trips every 3-4 months) to Philadelphia to meet the external stakeholders and running workshops, 1-2-1, presentations and demos
- Organising sprint planning, refinements, sprint reviews and retrospectives
- Working on new applications from concept stage after collecting high-level requirements, proposing a solution and leading all the way down to the design and delivery stage
- Working on integration with existing products and migrating data from existing products onto new applications
- Successfully delivered MVP in May 2019

Title: NBME CAS Project

Client: National Board of Medical Examiners

Year: May 2017-June 2019

Summary:

- Involved from pre-sales stage, working on technical requirements and proposing an overall solution
- Working on SoW for each release and creating features, user stories, providing cost and time estimates
- Making regular trips to Philadelphia to meet the external stakeholders and running workshops, 1-2-1, presentations and demos
- Organising sprint planning, refinements, sprint reviews and retrospectives
- A new web based application was proposed to meet client's requirements
- The application was integrated with a linear optimizer to generate optimized tests
- Application was hosted in Azure on the US hub
- MVP was successfully delivered in June 2019

Title: Prometric Development Client: Prometric United States Year: Jan 2015-August 2016

Summary:

- The project was aimed enhance Surpass (BTL's product) and create new modules within that i.e. Task
 Management, LOFT Testing using linear optimiser and integrating with a third party delivery application using
 QTI 2.1 and RESTful APIs
- Involved at the SoW stage, gathering requirements, performing gap analysis, proposing a solution and providing cost and time estimates
- Identifying features, writing user stories and acceptance criteria
- Organising sprint planning, review and retrospectives
- Giving demonstrations and presentation after every sprint to showcase the development
- Working closely with Technical Architect to provide infrastructure architecture and costs

Title: Safe City

Client: SingTel Singapore

Year: 2015 Summary:

- The project was aimed to create a new cloud based students registration and online exam delivery system to be used by 100s of schools across Singapore
- I was involved from pre-sales stage, worked closely with Singapore partners to understand technical requirements, providing infrastructure and application architecture, and providing cost and time estimates for all the phases of the project
- Regularly travelled to Singapore to give presentations and demonstrations and to run requirements gathering sessions
- Creating process flow diagrams, use cases, sequence diagrams, class diagrams, and database diagrams
- Providing updates to internal and external stakeholders about the project updates and development updates

Title: Analytics Reports Client: British Council

Year: 2014 Summary:

- The project was aimed to work closely with psychometricians and statisticians working for British Council to gather and analyse complicated analytics reports
- I worked very closely with statisticians at British Council to understand their reporting requirements
- Defining and writing the features
- Creating mock reports to get an approval from statisticians before creating features and writing acceptance criteria
- Guiding development teams to understand the complex requirements and monitoring the development
- Helping teams to test the reports before deploying them onto UAT

Title: Supplementary Resource Management System

Client: SQA Year: 2014 Summary:

- The project was aimed to provide a bespoke resource management system for SQA
- I lead this project all the way from concept stage to design and delivery
- Proposed a web based solution which was integrated with SQA external system for data and information exchange over RESTful APIs
- Creating features, user stories, writing acceptance criteria and organizing refinements sessions

Title: Analytics Application

Client: Royal College of Pediatrics and Child Health

Year: 2014 Summary:

- RCPCH delivers huge number of medical exams for doctors and its very important for them that the exams are balanced so they wanted to have an application which would integrate with their exam data and performs statistical analysis on items difficulty, average pass rate, test difficulty and more
- I lead this project all the way from concept stage to design and delivery
- Worked closely with RCPCH statisticians to understand their requirements
- I also created proposal, documented the requirements, created process maps, solution diagrams, UML artifacts, features, user stories, acceptance criteria, involved in sprint planning, and providing cost and time estimates
- Creating features, user stories, writing acceptance criteria and organizing refinements sessions

BUSINESS SYSTEMS DEVELOPER

BTL GROUP LTD (<u>www.btl.com</u>) Bradford, West Yorkshire, UK Aug 2009 – June 2013

As a developer, I have worked mainly in C#.Net, ASP.NET, and SQL Server. I was mainly responsible for developing within the main products, working on new features, and working on all integration requirements. I have also been responsible for building and deploying Surpass products using NAnt scripts.

TECHNOLOGIES/TOOLS: C#.NET, ASP.NET, SQL Server, XML, XSLT, ETL, SSIS, SSRS, SOAP

PROJECTS:

NAnt Scripts:

Building and deploying Surpass products using NAnt scripts.

EAL Integration Services:

As part of this project, I developed ETL packages using SQL Server Integration Services, .Net based windows services, and SOAP APIs using XML files.

TAP Integration Services:

The project involved writing .Net based web services, SQL Server 2005, integration based on SOAP and XML files.

NCFE Integration and Data Migration Services:

The project involved writing a custom application for NCFE to consume their existing data in the forms of XML files and transforming that data into Surpass expected format.

• AAT Integration and Data Migration Services:

This project was mainly aimed at writing a web based test delivery application for AAT, mainly written in C#.NET, ASP.NET, SQL Server.

Development in the Main Products:

The development involved C#.net, Flex, SQL Server, and SOAP based APIs.

WEB DEVELOPER

Cubic State LTD www.cubicstate.com)
Bradford, West Yorkshire, UK
Nov 2008 – April 2009

As a developer, I have worked mainly in C#.Net, ASP.NET, and SQL Server. The role also involved, writing new websites for clients using Cold Fusion, CSS and SQL Server 2005, HTML, and XML.

TECHNOLOGIES/TOOLS: C#.NET, ASP.NET, SQL Server, Cold Fusion, CSS, SQL, HTML, XML

STUDENTSHIP / SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

University of Bradford (https://www.bradford.ac.uk)
Bradford, West Yorkshire, UK
May 2008 – Nov 2008

During this job, my role was to gather and analyse the requirements, creating the web based user interface to upload QTI XML 2.1 packages. Writing business logic to process the packages and migrate items into local database. I was also involved in installing the Dspace repository, configuring it on the server and installation of Linux on university machines.

TECHNOLOGIES/TOOLS: QTI XML 2.1, XML, C#.NET, ASP.NET, SQL Server

LEISURE ACTIVITIES

My interests include travelling, cricket, badminton, table tennis and swimming.

LEISURE ACTIVITIES

References can be provided upon request.